Guide to the Kan'ichi Asakawa Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Kan'ichi Asakawa papers
1894-1994
1894-1955
MS 40
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
22.5
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, writings, notes, photographs, and miscellanea documenting the personal life and professional career of Kan'ichi Asakawa, a professor of Japanese history at Yale University and author of several books on Japanese history.
Asakawa, Kan'ichi, 1873-1948
Existence and Location of Copies
Boxes 1-10, 51-52, and 56-57 are available on microfilm (9715 frames on 10 reels, 35mm) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM201.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Kan'ichi Asakawa, 1946-1948; Mary Rouse, 1984; Yoshio Abe, 1984; and Jerome Pollitt, 1990; transferred from the East Asian Collection Curator, 2000-2001, 2004. Transferred from the East Asia Library, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiotape, videotape, and motion picture films, as well as preservation masters and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers needing to consult the original materials should consult the finding aid for policies governing reproduction for access.
Conditions Governing Access
Series I, Correspondence (Boxes 1-4), Series II, Diaries (Boxes 5-6), and Series III, Writings, Notes, and Miscellanea (Boxes 7-10, 51-52, and 56-57) are available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 201 instead of the originals.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and additions: I. Correspondence, 1895-1955. II. Diaries, 1900-1948. III. Writings, Notes, and Miscellanea, 1894-1940.
Biographical / Historical
Kan'ichi Asakawa was born in Nihommatsu, Japan, on December 20, 1873. He graduated from Waseda University (B.L., 1895), Dartmouth College (B.L., 1899), and Yale University (Ph.D., 1902). He taught Japanese history at Yale (1906-1942, professor emeritus, 1942-1948), and served as curator of Chinese and Japanese Collections (1907-1948). Asakawa wrote several books and articles on Japanese history. He died in West Wardsboro, Vermont, on August 11, 1948.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, writings, notes, photographs, and miscellanea documenting the personal life and professional career of Kan'ichi Asakawa, a professor of Japanese history at Yale University and author of several works on Japanese history. The Asakawa Papers are organized in three series:
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE, 1895-1955, contains letters to and from family members, beginning with Asakawa's first years in the United States, as a student at Dartmouth College and Yale University (1895-1902). Letters are written in both Japanese and English, depending on the correspondent. Additional correspondence relates to Asakawa's academic and literary interests, particularly his interest in Esperanto, an artificial language. Asakawa corresponded with David Morris and other members of the International Auxiliary Language Association on this topic. Letters written during World War II focus on the reaction of individuals to Japanese-Americans living in the United States and Asakawa's thoughts on this subject are often recorded in letters. A draft of a letter Asakawa wrote for President Franklin Delano Roosevelt to send to the Japanese emperor in order to prevent hostilities from commencing in 1941 is also arranged in this series.
SERIES II, DIARIES, 1900-1948, contains several volumes of personal journals from 1900-1925 and 1940-1948. Asakawa's early journals are those of a college student and young educator, and contain many references to the differences in culture he encountered as an immigrant from Japan. Later journals detail Asakawa's personal and professional activities, and, once again, material written during the years of World War II focuses on the responsibilities and treatment of Japanese-Americans.
SERIES III, WRITINGS, NOTES, AND MISCELLANEA, 1894-1940, consists of articles, essays, notes, photographs, student papers and other materials. The bulk of material relates to Japanese history, although a section of "Notes" contains research files on modern European and French history in addition to extensive files on Japanese history. Under the heading "Japanese chronicles" is a group of research notes on a wide variety of Japanese historical topics from 1172-1945. Material relating to the Yale Association of Japan (folders 288-292) and the Yale Japanese Club (folder 296) is also arranged in this series.
Esperanto; Japanese -- United States; World War, 1939-1945; Asia; Japan -- Civilization -- 1600-1868; Japan -- History -- 1926-1945; Japan -- History -- Restoration, 1835-1870; Diaries; Historians; Anderson, Mary, 1859-1940; Asakawa, Kan'ichi, 1873-1948; Morris, David; Navarro, António Rebordão; Navarro, José Maria de, 1900-; Painter, Sidney, 1902-1960; Parsons, Alfred, 1847-1920; Sturges, Alice Vanderbilt Morris; Shimazu family; Yale Association of Japan; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1895-1955; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in two sections: General and Select. General is arranged in chronological order. Select is arranged in alphabetical order, with résumés filed at the end of the section.
  Conditions Governing Access
  These materials are available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 201 instead of the originals.
  - General
    - 1895-1906 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 14)
    - 1907-1929 (Box 2, Folder 15 - 26)
    - 1930-1955 (Box 3, Folder 27 - 38)
  - Select
    - Asakawa family, 1895, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Booth, ______, 1906-1926 (Box 4, Folder 40 - 41)
    - Privy Councilor, (Count K), 1941 October 10 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1941 November 23 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Résumés, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Diaries, 1900-1948; Series II
  This series contains diaries arranged in chronological order, with no material for the years 1926-1939.
  - Diaries, 1900-1925 October 11 (Box 5, Folder 45 - 53)
  - Diaries, 1940 July 28-1948 August 8 (Box 6, Folder 54 - 56)
- Writings, Notes, and Miscellanea, 1894-1940; Series III
  This series contains material arranged in alphabetical order by topic, with "miscellanea" filed at the end of the section.
  - Addresses, 1895-1940 (Box 7, Folder 57 - 66)
  - Appointment book, 1911-1925 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Articles, 1905-1931 (Box 7, Folder 68 - 70)
  - Book reviews, 1930-1931 (Box 7, Folder 71 - 72)
  - Books, undated (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Essays
    - General (Box 7, Folder 74 - 79)
    - Japan (Box 8, Folder 80 - 93)
    - Japan (Box 9, Folder 94 - 99)
    - "Nature of Feudal Society" (Box 10, Folder 100 - 109)
  - Guest book, 1907-1911 (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - Notes
    - Modern European history (Box 11)
    - Modern European history (Box 12)
    - Modern European history (Box 13)
    - Modern French history (Box 14)
    - Modern French history (Box 15)
    - Modern French history (Box 16)
    - Modern French history (Box 17)
    - Modern French history (Box 18)
    - Modern French history (Box 19)
    - Modern French history (Box 20)
    - Modern French history (Box 21)
    - Modern French history (Box 22)
    - Modern French history (Box 23)
    - Modern French history (Box 24)
    - Japanese history
      - General (Box 25)
      - General (Box 26)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 27)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 28)
      - Ancient history (Box 29)
      - Ancient history (Box 30)
      - Shimazu (Box 31)
      - Shimazu (Box 32)
      - Shimazu (Box 33)
      - Shimazu (Box 34)
      - Family (Box 35)
      - Emperors (Box 36)
      - Japanese society (Box 37, Folder 111 - 117)
      - Japanese chronicles
        - 1172-1699 (Box 38, Folder 118 - 125)
        - 1700-1857 (Box 39, Folder 126 -135)
        - 1858-1863 (Box 40, Folder 136 - 146)
        - 1864-1871 (Box 41, Folder 147 - 155)
        - 1872-1933 (Box 42, Folder 156 - 166)
        - 1934-1936 (Box 43, Folder 167 - 173)
        - 1937-1940 (Box 44, Folder 174 - 181)
        - 1941-1945 (Box 45, Folder 182 - 187)
      - Lectures: Dartmouth College and Japan, 1894-1907 (Box 46, Folder 188 - 197)
      - Philosophy and history
        - Ancient Germans-Greek history (Box 47, Folder 198 - 211)
        - Indies-man and person (Box 48, Folder 212 - 218)
        - Nation and individuals-Roman law (Box 49, Folder 219 - 229)
        - World history-miscellanea (Box 50, Folder 230 - 234)
  - Papers (Box 51, Folder 235 - 237)
  - Photographs
    - Groups (Box 52, Folder 238)
    - Portraits (Box 52, Folder 239)
    - Miscellanea (Box 52, Folder 240)
  - Printed material (Box 53, Folder 241 - 244)
  - Printed material (Box 54, Folder 245 - 247)
  - Student materials
    - Exams (Box 55, Folder 248 - 252)
    - Papers (Box 56, Folder 253 - 272)
  - Translations (Box 57, Folder 273 - 287)
  - Miscellanea
    - "Gifts of the Yale Association of Japan" (Box 58, Folder 288 - 292)
    - Maps (Box 58, Folder 293)
    - Notebook (Box 58, Folder 294)
    - Postal cards (Box 58, Folder 295)
    - Scrolls (Box 59)
    - Yale Japanese Club [1870-1922], 1907-1922 (Box 60, Folder 296)
  - Abe Yoshio, Saigo no Nihonjin: Asakawa Kanichi no shogai, 1983 (Box 61, Folder 297)
- Additional Material, Accession 1991-M-041
  - Correspondence from Kan'ichi Asakawa to others, 1941 Dec, 1942 Jan, Mar, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address by Kan'ichi Asakawa, 1943 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Shortscript: A New Rapid Handwriting, by A. Maertz, and H. Asakawa's analysis of, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical material, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Hartley Simpson pertaining to Kan'ichi Asakawa, 1948 September-Nov, 1949 March-Apr, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notes by Hartley Simpson pertaining to Kan'ichi Asakawa's diary, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - List of history courses pertaining primarily to Japan, 1907-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photograph of Kan'ichi Asakawa, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence between George Pierson and Hideo Kaneko pertaining to Kaneko's tribute to Kan'ichi Asakawa in Nota Bene (transferred from Librarian's Office on 1991 Jan 8), 1990 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Additional Material, Accession 2001-M-013
  - Correspondence
    - Tokutomi, Soho [includes Chinese poem], 1930 January 7, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified [sent to Asakawa c/o Waseda University Library], Circa 1906 or 1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Writings
    - "Allotment of Rice-Land: A Sketch", 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Japanese Personal Names" [cataloging of], 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Transliteration and Hyphenation", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Untitled glossary of terms [presumably handwritten by Asakawa], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia
    - Kokeshi doll [traditional wooden doll presented to Yale by Taka Okochi, mayor of Nihommatsu, Japan, hometown of Asakawa], 1993 August (Box 2)
    - "Harukanaru kobo" [a biography of Asakawa], 1985; 1 (Box 3)
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
- Additional Material, Accession 2001-M-082
  - Telementary '94 Maboroshi no daitoryoshinsho - Kaisen o soshi sh'yoto shita otoko [videotape of Japanese television program documenting Asakawa's efforts to have President Roosevelt write a letter to the Japanese emperor just before the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor], 1994 December 11 (Box 1)
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site. Copies of commercially produced audiovisual materials contained in this collection cannot be made for researcher use outside of the repository.
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-011
  - Asakawa's notes on a lecture given by Oya on art in the Meiji period, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Paper on Byron submitted to Tokyo Senmon Gakko (predecessor to Waseda University) seminar?, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Undergraduate thesis by Asakawa at Tokyo Senmon Gakko (predecessor to Waseda University), 1895 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter to Asakawa from an unidentified sender in Tokyo, [1908] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Document on the language of Izu Peninsula, author unknown, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lecture notes on ethics by Asakawa, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, possibly notes from a lecture attended by Asakawa, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Additional Material, Accession 2010-M-007
  - Photographic prints of Asakawa with a brief description of each, 1892-circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The prints include school, family, and passport photographs, with an English translation of captions.